<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed
  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0"
  xml:lang="en-US"
  xml:base="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/wp-atom.php"
   >
	<title type="text">Just So</title>
	<subtitle type="text">Meditations on Enlightenment</subtitle>

	<updated>2012-06-23T02:50:29Z</updated>

	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" />
	<id>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/feed/atom/</id>
	<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/feed/atom/" />

	<generator uri="http://wordpress.org/" version="3.4.1">WordPress</generator>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>mikael</name>
						<uri>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com</uri>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[The world of being]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-world-of-being/" />
		<id>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/?p=973</id>
		<updated>2012-06-23T02:50:29Z</updated>
		<published>2012-06-23T02:50:29Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Zen" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="awareness" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="dna" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="ego" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="god" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="illusion" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="survival" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="The marks of existence" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[The ego is an interesting thing. You have one. I have one. Yet it only exists as much as WordPress (the blog software I&#8217;m using) exists, and in much the same kind of way. The ego is part of the software of the mind, constructed by the mind. It is reinforced from an incredibly early [...]]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-world-of-being/"><![CDATA[<p>The ego is an interesting thing.  You have one. I have one.  Yet it only exists as much as WordPress (the blog software I&#8217;m using) exists, and in much the same kind of way.  The ego is part of the software of the mind, constructed by the mind.  It is reinforced from an incredibly early age, but I is not the first thing that comes out of a child&#8217;s mouth.  &#8220;Juice&#8221; was my first&#8217;s first word. And programming, as much as almost all of it is done is with words.  The point though isn&#8217;t about words, the point is about ego.</p>
<p>The sense of I arises out of a sense of separation.  And the world of form certainly gives aids in this illusion. Those of us who see, see objects all around.  It is not difficult to believe that they&#8217;re separate and for us to believe that we&#8217;re separate as well.  Refining distinctions is how we make sense of the world, and how we master our experience of it. (Note I didn&#8217;t say master the world. That&#8217;s too arrogant an assumption for my small brain.)  And understandably we infer that we are also separate beings. But it&#8217;s a trick, an illusion created by our brains, to aid in the survival of the DNA.  Yet, here is the very first sense of suffering.  The creation of the ego in the mind is the beginning of suffering.</p>
<p>Armed with images, sounds and words, the mind starts to build a view of itself.  Everything it sees has qualities. It&#8217;s this colour or that, large or small, good or bad, hungry or replete.  And so it begins to describe itself, aided of course by its unwitting parents. Some would also add that tendencies from previous rebirths get thrown into the mix as well, but for many that&#8217;s moot so I won&#8217;t dwell on it.  And the now the ego begins to cling to qualities to affirm itself in the world.</p>
<p>But no list of qualities is complete.  There is always something missing.  No matter how much the mind, perceiving itself as an ego, tries to add to itself, refine itself, it is never good enough.  But the mind clings to this ego and stubbornly continues to believe that perfection must be possible.  And here is the struggle and the cause of all of the rest of the suffering.  Perfection is not possible, not in this limited sense.</p>
<p>And every time the mind perceiving itself as an ego thinks it has things worked out, along comes change and smacks the poor ego and says &#8220;not this time.&#8221;  So the mind as ego suffers and then adapts to the new circumstances.</p>
<p>Yet all along the ego never really existed.  It all started with a misunderstanding, misidentification with the world of objects, the world of how things appear to be, not how things are.  The mind is not some identity.</p>
<p>And there we have it, my interpretation of the world of being:- imperfection, no identity, and impermanence.  What an incredible joke that we have seen ourselves this way, and what a tragedy that we have had to endure so much suffering.</p>
<p>Our pure awareness, holy God, creator and destroyer of all that is, may I return to your bosom and know myself as nothing at all.</p>
<p><a class="a2a_dd a2a_target addtoany_share_save" href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save#url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.mikaelaldridge.com%2Fzen%2Fthe-world-of-being%2F&amp;title=The%20world%20of%20being" id="wpa2a_2">Share/Bookmark</a></p>]]></content>
		<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-world-of-being/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-world-of-being/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>mikael</name>
						<uri>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com</uri>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Primitivism]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/primitivism/" />
		<id>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/?p=963</id>
		<updated>2012-06-04T03:53:14Z</updated>
		<published>2012-06-04T01:38:22Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Politics" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Zen" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="altruism" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="buddhism" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="buddhist perspective" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="cat owner" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="chimpanzee" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="civilization" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="consumerism" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="human beings" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="indigenous population" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="infanticide" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="killer whale" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Maori" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="new territory" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="paradise on earth" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="primitive societies" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="primitive state" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="state of affairs" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="tendencies" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="white man" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[There is an idea out there amongst some practitioners that what we need to do, as human beings, is return to some primitive state and that we&#8217;ll be fine. The problem they argue is that civilisation has perverted our innate altruistic tendencies. Yet, the buddhist perspective is that ignorance is primordial, that we need to [...]]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/primitivism/"><![CDATA[<p>There is an idea out there amongst some practitioners that what we need to do, as human beings, is return to some primitive state and that we&#8217;ll be fine.  The problem they argue is that civilisation has perverted our innate altruistic tendencies.</p>
<p>Yet, the buddhist perspective is that ignorance is primordial, that we need to uproot it, see things as they truly are, and we will be free of suffering. You only have to look as far as humanity&#8217;s nearest living relative, the common chimpanzee, to see that the primitive state isn&#8217;t so fine.  Prone to occasional cannibalism, infanticide and a willingness to kill to gain new territory reveal a rather unenlightened state of affairs.</p>
<p><center><object width="425" height="350" classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="src" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/CPznMbNcfO8&amp;feature" /><embed width="425" height="350" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" src="http://www.youtube.com/v/CPznMbNcfO8&amp;feature" /></object></center></p>
<p>Any cat owner has probably witnessed their pet&#8217;s delight in torturing a bird or mouse.  And we need only look to how the killer whale plays and tortures seals to see that cruelty exists outside of hominids.  Yes, there a plenty of cases of animal altruism, but the point is that it&#8217;s not the only state of affairs.</p>
<p>Nor have primitive societies lived in primordial bliss.  New Zealand&#8217;s indigenous population wiped out 43 species before the arrival of white man.  That they learned from it and institutionalised environmentalism through a system of tapu is to their credit.  But it took another more dominant race to bring the Maori&#8217;s cannibalism to an end.  Don&#8217;t think that I am criticising the Maori here. White man&#8217;s consumerism is even more deadly and we still haven&#8217;t learned from it. More credit to the Maori.</p>
<p>Buddhism argues that ignorance is primordial and Zen argues that we have to move beyond thinking, not before it into some instinctive state.  We have to let go of clinging, just doing that will end consumerism.  We have to let go of harming others, and that will create a paradise on earth.  We have to let go of the idea that we&#8217;re separate beings, and that will end our identification with suffering.</p>
<p>This is an evolution and a massive revolution. It is a reversal of our instinctive, ignorant state of being not a return to it.  It&#8217;s hard work because it moves us beyond our comfort zone.  It&#8217;s liberating.</p>
<p><a class="a2a_dd a2a_target addtoany_share_save" href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save#url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.mikaelaldridge.com%2Fzen%2Fprimitivism%2F&amp;title=Primitivism" id="wpa2a_4">Share/Bookmark</a></p>]]></content>
		<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/primitivism/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/primitivism/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>mikael</name>
						<uri>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com</uri>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Sentient beings give rise to buddhas]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/sentient-beings-2/" />
		<id>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/?p=956</id>
		<updated>2012-06-04T03:19:14Z</updated>
		<published>2012-05-27T06:24:56Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Zen" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="dharma" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="erroneous view" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="feelings" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="gates" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="hiandrances" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Hui Neng" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="impermanence" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="initiation" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="insight" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="liberation" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="prajna" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="proceeds" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="psyche" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="sense objects" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="sense organs" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="senses" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="six sense" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[Observing the rising and falling of thoughts and the rising and falling of feeling is central to my practice. It has a number of benefits. Firstly, it gives insight into the space between thoughts. I&#8217;ve been calling that awareness of late. It strikes me that this is the &#8220;essence of mind&#8221; that Hui Neng talks [...]]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/sentient-beings-2/"><![CDATA[<p>Observing the rising and falling of thoughts and the rising and falling of feeling is central to my practice.  It has a number of benefits.  Firstly, it gives insight into the space between thoughts. I&#8217;ve been calling that awareness of late. It strikes me that this is the &#8220;essence of mind&#8221; that Hui Neng talks about.  Secondly, it demonstrates the impermanence of thoughts, points of view and of feelings. And that leads to the fourth point, which is that the whole realm of appearances is unsatisfactory.  Fifthly, it develops a kind of spaciousness in one&#8217;s psyche.</p>
<p>In a way this post proceeds on from &#8220;<a href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-second-initiation/" title="The second initiation">The second initiation</a>.&#8221; Seeing feelings arise, eventually gives the ability to intercept them and examine how that feeling will move into craving, into clinging, into becoming, into birth and into suffering; even if you&#8217;re watching it happen in real time. Seeing from your own experience that feelings lead to suffering is a vital key. </p>
<p>Also of interest to this post is how the senses lead to contact and in turn lead to feeling for me is such an exquisite part of the dharma.  </p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;What we have to do is to purify our mind so that the six vijnanas (types of consciousness), in passing through the six gates (sense organs) will neither be defiled by nor attached to the six sense-objects. When our mind works freely without any hindrance, and is at liberty to &#8216;come&#8217; or to &#8216;go&#8217;, we attain Samadhi of Prajna, or liberation. Such a state is called the function of &#8216;thoughtlessness&#8217;. But to refrain from thinking of anything, so that all thoughts are suppressed, is to be Dharma-ridden, and this is an erroneous view.&#8221;<br />
Hui Neng
</p></blockquote>
<p>The point of all of this is: if you don&#8217;t see the flow of suffering, you won&#8217;t know how to stop it.  Once you see how it all works for yourself, you want to stop it. Why should you suffer any more?  And you want to enter fully into that awareness you&#8217;ve discovered.</p>
<p>The technique is that you can be simply aware, you can intercept thoughts and you can intercept feelings. There is lots of room for practice.</p>
<p>&#8220;Sentient beings who sow the seeds of enlightenment In the field of causation will reap the fruit of Buddhahood.&#8221;</p>
<p><a class="a2a_dd a2a_target addtoany_share_save" href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save#url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.mikaelaldridge.com%2Fzen%2Fsentient-beings-2%2F&amp;title=Sentient%20beings%20give%20rise%20to%20buddhas" id="wpa2a_6">Share/Bookmark</a></p>]]></content>
		<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/sentient-beings-2/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/sentient-beings-2/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>mikael</name>
						<uri>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com</uri>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[There is nothing to be added]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/there-is-nothing-to-be-added/" />
		<id>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/?p=950</id>
		<updated>2012-05-10T22:54:13Z</updated>
		<published>2012-05-10T22:51:43Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Zen" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[One day Banzan was walking through a market. He overheard a customer say to the butcher, &#8220;Give me the best piece of meat you have.&#8221; &#8220;Everything in my shop is the best,&#8221; replied the butcher. &#8220;You can not find any piece of meat that is not the best.&#8221; At these words, Banzan was enlightened.]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/there-is-nothing-to-be-added/"><![CDATA[<p>One day Banzan was walking through a market. He overheard a customer say to the butcher, &#8220;Give me the best piece of meat you have.&#8221; &#8220;Everything in my shop is the best,&#8221; replied the butcher. &#8220;You can not find any piece of meat that is not the best.&#8221; At these words, Banzan was enlightened.</p>
<p><a class="a2a_dd a2a_target addtoany_share_save" href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save#url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.mikaelaldridge.com%2Fzen%2Fthere-is-nothing-to-be-added%2F&amp;title=There%20is%20nothing%20to%20be%20added" id="wpa2a_8">Share/Bookmark</a></p>]]></content>
		<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/there-is-nothing-to-be-added/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/there-is-nothing-to-be-added/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>mikael</name>
						<uri>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com</uri>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[The flow of being]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-flow-of-being/" />
		<id>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/?p=947</id>
		<updated>2012-05-16T00:10:32Z</updated>
		<published>2012-04-22T09:03:40Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Zen" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="awareness" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="delusion" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="emptiness" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="heraclitus" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="karma" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="non-duality" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Thich Nhat Hanh" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[Non- is an interesting prefix in modern Buddhism. It tends to get used in a non-dualistic way. In other words, the opposite of attachment is detachment, but if we want to talk about neither attachment nor detachment, we would use the word non-attachment. Non-duality is kind of like that too. This points to the idea [...]]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-flow-of-being/"><![CDATA[<p>Non- is an interesting prefix in modern Buddhism. It tends to get used in a non-dualistic way.  In other words, the opposite of attachment is detachment, but if we want to talk about neither attachment nor detachment, we would use the word non-attachment.  Non-duality is kind of like that too.  This points to the idea that what we are talking about is beyond dualistic thinking, or the pairs of opposites as it used to be called in occult literature.</p>
<p>Thich Nhat Hanh pointed out that in every piece of paper is a cloud.  I told this to  my five year old niece the other day.  And then explained to her that without clouds there would be no rain, and without the rain there would be no trees, and without the trees there would be no paper. She got it.  &#8220;It still sounds strange though,&#8221; she replied. This is a revolution of thinking, of course it does.</p>
<p>Thich Nhat Hanh calls this Interbeing, some buddhists think this is an aspect of dependent co-arising, and I agree.  In one sense we are who we are dependent on our parents, on the society we live in, on the people we mix with in our daily lives to be who we are.  Moreover we participate in creating society around us, and the people around us who they are.  In one breath we can say that we are responsible for everything being the way it is and also say &#8220;I am not my fault.&#8221;  Neither and both.  </p>
<p>Heraclitus, a Greek philosopher, said that you can&#8217;t step in the same river twice because by the time you step in it again the river will have changed.  It will be different water, different fish, different shapes on the river banks.  Just as importantly it won&#8217;t even be the same you.  You will have changed.  The you which has co-dependently arisen will have been changed by your experiences.  All that you can really say, and you can&#8217;t even say that, is that there is this massive flux.  There is certainly no separate permanent you, at all, not even for a second. So don&#8217;t delude yourself.</p>
<p>Delusion is exactly what we do.  Rather than seeing this massive flux, we particularise.  We see discrete fixed objects, and we give them names.  And to make things worse we make them good and bad.  We cling to our objectifications like a limpet. We define ourselves in terms of our experiences, of our objectified senses, of our objectifying thoughts.  As a result, we suffer.  When we create good, we create bad.</p>
<p>Yet all the time there is this miraculous awareness. Aware of the passing thoughts, experiences, and just aware in itself. Why define ourselves at all?  This awareness doesn&#8217;t need definition.  Try it.  Whatever you define it as, it&#8217;s not that.  Some would argue that the gateway to this understanding is concentration, but held within a context of not identifying with the thoughts and experiences as they arise. Try it, but don&#8217;t become attached to it.</p>
<p>What can we say about it? Or in saying anything have we just objectified and created a new delusion?</p>
<p><a class="a2a_dd a2a_target addtoany_share_save" href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save#url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.mikaelaldridge.com%2Fzen%2Fthe-flow-of-being%2F&amp;title=The%20flow%20of%20being" id="wpa2a_10">Share/Bookmark</a></p>]]></content>
		<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-flow-of-being/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-flow-of-being/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>mikael</name>
						<uri>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com</uri>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[The Second Initiation]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-second-initiation/" />
		<id>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/?p=933</id>
		<updated>2012-03-22T04:35:11Z</updated>
		<published>2012-03-21T00:06:40Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Zen" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Alice Bailey" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Baptism" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="initiation" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Sotapanna" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[In Just what is an arhat? I talked a little about the fifth initiation. Western occultism&#8217;s second initiation is said to be the same as the Buddhist stage of stream winner. I think it would be kind of interesting to explore this. So let&#8217;s do it. A stream winner, or srotapanna in Sanskrit and sotapanna [...]]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-second-initiation/"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/just-what-is-an-arhat/">Just what is an arhat?</a> I talked a little about the fifth initiation. Western occultism&#8217;s second initiation is said to be the same as the Buddhist stage of stream winner. I think it would be kind of interesting to explore this. So let&#8217;s do it.</p>
<p>A stream winner, or srotapanna in Sanskrit and sotapanna in Pali, is someone who has entered the stream, of the buddhist eightfold noble path that leads to the end of suffering. Such a being has tasted nirvana and thus knows the truth of buddha&#8217;s teaching. He has more than likely achieved this through meditation.</p>
<p>Importantly, because they have tasted nirvana, they have no more doubt. But this is also because meditation has enabled them to penetrate into form and see that there is no self there. This maybe requires some explanation. Traditionally a Buddhist sees the personality as composed of the five aggregates:-form, sensation, perception, mental formations, consciousness. But there is an approach nearer to our culture that does the job just as well.</p>
<p>In the neo-Darwin school, we are nothing more than a mechanism for the survival of our genes. Acquisition whether that&#8217;s of things, or personal characteristics is nothing than to ensure the survival of the genes. Richard Dawkins called them the selfish gene. In other words what you think of as your identity has nothing to do with you whatsoever, your identity is nothing other than a strategy by your genes to ensure that they will reproduce. Money, power, and social status are mechanisms through which your selfish genes compete. This gives rise to what you think, feel and experience. Almost all people find this very difficult to accept. But this denial too is nothing other than part of the strategy of the genes.  To see evidence of this you need look no further than a breed of dog or cat.  Why?  Because whole breeds share personalities.  Your personality is not in fact yours.  It&#8217;s merely an expression of your genes.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s hope. Meditate enough and you will discover that your awareness lies as a substrate beneath thoughts, feelings and bodily sensations, which are fluid. Your awareness lies beneath your personality even. And of course you see the impermanence of these thoughts, feelings and bodily sensations. In a sense your genes have captured your awareness, but identifying with them will only lead to suffering for the simple reason that they vanish soon enough and your clinging to them lead to misery. So, it&#8217;s awareness that&#8217;s interesting and has interestingly enough been there all the time. It&#8217;s just that we&#8217;ve failed to pay due attention to it. Disidentify the awareness from its content and you will be free.</p>
<p>This view that all form is empty of self is only one part of the understanding. Another part is the interconnectedness of all things. This is not as new age as it might otherwise sound. It is in part an understanding that we have been making a huge mistake by reifying, i.e. creating things. Ask yourself this, when is a tree no longer a seed and then a tree? A tree is really one huge process. Moreover it doesn&#8217;t stand in isolation. It depends on the rain, the soil, the sun, the wind, other plants, animals, etc. etc. etc. Everything as much as there are things is interdependent. That we see things as separate is nothing other than a convenient fiction.</p>
<p>So our disciple gets the point and decides to move from identification with form and a separative view to identification with awareness and a holistic interdependent view, realizing that he his not the contents of the awareness, realizing that the contents of awareness are without any self, realizing that everything is interconnected and puts the truth into practice and renounces all separate and form identity.</p>
<p>So how does this match with the western occultism&#8217;s view? The alignment isn&#8217;t as complete as you might wish, but it&#8217;s revealing nevertheless. It centers around the purification of the emotional nature.</p>
<p>In the west this initiation is sometimes called the initiation of the Baptism. Christ was said to have taken the second initiation when John the Baptist submerged Jesus into the stream. At the second initiation the disciple has purified his emotional nature and is ready to be born again into the kingdom of heaven.</p>
<p>The normal human identity is rooted in the emotional nature. Few are the people with a true mental identification, which is why the second initiation is much more difficult than the other for most people. To give up identification with the emotional nature is to give up most of the sense of one&#8217;s self. It helps to know that emotions arise as a result of wrong view. That identification with thoughts is another wrong view, is to the western occultist a matter of the third initiation, and a mater for another post.</p>
<p>There is a slight mismatch between the Western occultist&#8217;s view point and a Buddhist&#8217;s. In one view the disciple has given up identity and doubt, to the other he has given up desire.  But as we saw the root of identity for most is in the emotional nature.</p>
<p>At the second initiation the disciple has struck a major blow at the sense of I, such that all that&#8217;s left are some habits. Buddha was very clear about that.</p>
<blockquote><p>Buddha then asked, &#8220;What do you think, Subhuti, does one who has entered the stream which flows to Enlightenment, say &#8216;I have entered the stream&#8217;?&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;No, Buddha&#8221;, Subhuti replied. &#8220;A true disciple entering the stream would not think of themselves as a separate person that could be entering anything. Only that disciple who does not differentiate themselves from others, who has no regard for name, shape, sound, odor, taste, touch or for any quality can truly be called a disciple who has entered the stream.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p><a class="a2a_dd a2a_target addtoany_share_save" href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save#url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.mikaelaldridge.com%2Fzen%2Fthe-second-initiation%2F&amp;title=The%20Second%20Initiation" id="wpa2a_12">Share/Bookmark</a></p>]]></content>
		<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-second-initiation/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/the-second-initiation/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>mikael</name>
						<uri>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com</uri>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Jesus lived in India]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/jesus-lived-in-india/" />
		<id>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/?p=922</id>
		<updated>2011-12-04T20:00:58Z</updated>
		<published>2011-12-04T04:56:06Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Zen" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been reading a lot of Shantideva&#8217;s The Way of the Boddhisattva lately. It strikes me that it has a very Christian flavour, so much so that I have been wondering if Shantideva was a reincarnation of Jesus. My brother came around for dinner last night and he was telling me about this documentary [...]]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/jesus-lived-in-india/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been reading a lot of Shantideva&#8217;s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1590306147?ie=UTF8&tag=jusstu-20&linkCode=as2&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=1590306147">The Way of the Boddhisattva</a> lately. It strikes me that it has a very Christian flavour, so much so that I have been wondering if Shantideva was a reincarnation of Jesus. My brother came around for dinner last night and he was telling me about this documentary he had seen (see below) that Christ was a Buddha.</p>
<p>It reminded me of a book in my library called <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1852305509?ie=UTF8&tag=jusstu-20&linkCode=as2&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=1852305509">Jesus Lived in India</a> by Holger Kersten, which goes into a lot more detail on the subject.  He draws on the apocryphal Gospel of Thomas. Much of the material covered in the BBC documentary is drawn from the same material.   </p>
<p>The Bible doesn&#8217;t overly suit my type of mind.  Neither do lot of Buddhist texts for that matter.  In my mind there are no -isms or -anities.  What religion is there other than the luminous mind? Gods, devas, and miracles aren&#8217;t really my cup of tea as awareness is miraculous enough for me.  Nevertheless, as I recall, the Gospel of Thomas (in the apocrypha) talks about Thomas, Mary and Jesus heading down to India.</p>
<p><center><object width="425" height="350" classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="src" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/-YbUEZfJJaQ&amp;feature" /><embed width="425" height="350" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" src="http://www.youtube.com/v/-YbUEZfJJaQ&amp;feature" /></object></center></p>
<p>In the esoteric school I did my early training in, one of the basic beliefs was that Christ was none other than Maitreya Buddha.  It all gets a bit complex about the relationship between Christ and Jesus, not that it really matters.  One of the views as much I understood it was that Buddha perfected wisdom, creating the religion for the East, and Christ perfected love, creating the religion for the West.  Two sides of the same coin.</p>
<p>To that end, the other day, I was listening to a FBA lecture where the basic premise was that for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodhicitta">bodhicitta</a> to arise you had to simultaneously detach from the world and engage your fellow beings through loving kindness.</p>
<p><a class="a2a_dd a2a_target addtoany_share_save" href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save#url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.mikaelaldridge.com%2Fzen%2Fjesus-lived-in-india%2F&amp;title=Jesus%20lived%20in%20India" id="wpa2a_14">Share/Bookmark</a></p>]]></content>
		<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/jesus-lived-in-india/#comments" thr:count="2"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/jesus-lived-in-india/feed/atom/" thr:count="2"/>
		<thr:total>2</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>mikael</name>
						<uri>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com</uri>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Mahakasyapa&#8217;s flower]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/mahakasyapas-flower/" />
		<id>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/?p=917</id>
		<updated>2011-11-26T04:56:13Z</updated>
		<published>2011-11-26T04:56:13Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Zen" /><category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="poem" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[A dead stem standing. Rank water. Petals scattered. Something remembered.]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/mahakasyapas-flower/"><![CDATA[<p>A dead stem standing.<br />
Rank water.<br />
Petals scattered.<br />
Something remembered.</p>
<p><a class="a2a_dd a2a_target addtoany_share_save" href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save#url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.mikaelaldridge.com%2Fzen%2Fmahakasyapas-flower%2F&amp;title=Mahakasyapa%E2%80%99s%20flower" id="wpa2a_16">Share/Bookmark</a></p>]]></content>
		<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/mahakasyapas-flower/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/mahakasyapas-flower/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>mikael</name>
						<uri>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com</uri>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Chiyono’s awakening]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/chiyono%e2%80%99s-awakening/" />
		<id>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/?p=881</id>
		<updated>2011-12-01T23:21:46Z</updated>
		<published>2011-11-25T04:39:38Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Zen" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[The story goes that Chiyono was incredibly beautiful. And for this reason, as much as she tried, she was refused entry into zen monasteries. The masters claimed that she would drive the monks mad. One day she burned her face to the point where she was not recognisable as man or woman; and she was [...]]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/chiyono%e2%80%99s-awakening/"><![CDATA[<p>The story goes that Chiyono was incredibly beautiful. And for this reason, as much as she tried, she was refused entry into zen monasteries. The masters claimed that she would drive the monks mad. One day she burned her face to the point where she was not recognisable as man or woman; and she was permitted to study in the monastery.</p>
<p>Despite this amazing and perhaps courageous act, enlightenment didn&#8217;t come quickly to Chiyono. However, she was a deteremined student. At last, one moonlit night, she ﬁlled her old water bucket from a well (a well that centuries later would still bear her name). As she walked away, she saw the full moon reﬂected on the surface of the water. As she continued along the path, the circular bamboo strip gave way that had held together the staves of her bucket. Instantly, the bottom broke through, the moon’s reﬂection vanished, the bucket disintegrated, and all its water drained into the soil beneath. At this moment, Chiyono experienced a sudden, penetrating ﬂash of insight-wisdom.</p>
<p>She later explained it this way: ‘‘I had hoped the weak bamboo binding would hold the water bucket together. But suddenly the bottom fell out of the bucket: no more water. No more moon in the water. Emptiness in my hand!’’</p>
<p><a class="a2a_dd a2a_target addtoany_share_save" href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save#url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.mikaelaldridge.com%2Fzen%2Fchiyono%25e2%2580%2599s-awakening%2F&amp;title=Chiyono%E2%80%99s%20awakening" id="wpa2a_18">Share/Bookmark</a></p>]]></content>
		<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/chiyono%e2%80%99s-awakening/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/chiyono%e2%80%99s-awakening/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
		<entry>
		<author>
			<name>mikael</name>
						<uri>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com</uri>
					</author>
		<title type="html"><![CDATA[Happiness]]></title>
		<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/happiness/" />
		<id>http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/?p=909</id>
		<updated>2011-11-22T05:34:12Z</updated>
		<published>2011-11-22T05:34:12Z</published>
		<category scheme="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com" term="Zen" />		<summary type="html"><![CDATA[I can&#8217;t believe I&#8217;ve wasted so much time and energy trying to be happy.  It reminds me of a Taiji book called &#8220;There are no secrets.&#8221;  It seems that the root problem lies in clinging to a sense of self &#8211; identity and identification.  Enlightenment is our birth right.  It&#8217;s who we are.  Yet, it&#8217;s [...]]]></summary>
		<content type="html" xml:base="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/happiness/"><![CDATA[<p>I can&#8217;t believe I&#8217;ve wasted so much time and energy trying to be happy.  It reminds me of a Taiji book called &#8220;There are no secrets.&#8221;  It seems that the root problem lies in clinging to a sense of self &#8211; identity and identification.  Enlightenment is our birth right.  It&#8217;s who we are.  Yet, it&#8217;s the sense of self that creates clinging to desire and to anger and to a sense of being disconnected.</p>
<p>We can put so much energy into ending wanting and ending anger.  And some good can be done that way.  What greater good is there in abandoning a sense of self!  Not good in some pseudo-intellectual way.  Good in what makes us happy.  What is the point in feeling anxiety?  I really like Shantideva&#8217;s observation</p>
<blockquote><p>All those who fail to understand<br />
The secret of the mind, the greatest of all things,<br />
Although they wish for joy and sorrow&#8217;s end,<br />
Will wander to no purpose, useleslly.</p>
<p>Therefore I will take in hand<br />
And well protect this mind of mine.<br />
What use to me are many disciplines,<br />
If I can&#8217;t guard and discipline my mind?</p></blockquote>
<p>Thank you.</p>
<p><a class="a2a_dd a2a_target addtoany_share_save" href="http://www.addtoany.com/share_save#url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.mikaelaldridge.com%2Fzen%2Fhappiness%2F&amp;title=Happiness" id="wpa2a_20">Share/Bookmark</a></p>]]></content>
		<link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/happiness/#comments" thr:count="0"/>
		<link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.mikaelaldridge.com/zen/happiness/feed/atom/" thr:count="0"/>
		<thr:total>0</thr:total>
	</entry>
	</feed>
